Guide to the Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize photography collection, 1996-2019 RL.00795
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize photography collection
1996-2019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McAdams, Dona Ann
Lommasson, Jim
Eskenazi, Jason
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
Berridge, Mary
Amberg, Rob
Ramos, Daniel, 1978-
RL.00795
10 Linear Feet 8 boxes 91 prints
36 Gigabytes 4 digital video files in .mov, .wmv, and mp4 formats (Cozart collection)
The Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor documentary prize is awarded by Duke University's Center for Documentary Studies to a writer and a photographer in the early stages of a documentary project. The collection houses the work of seven documentary artists, all recipients of the Lange-Taylor Prize: Rob Amberg, Mary Berridge, Steven Cozart, Jason Eskenazi, Jim Lommasson, Dona Ann McAdams, and Daniel Ramos. Their portfolios total 91 color and black-and-white photographic prints, some of them image collages, and four oral history digital videos. The projects examine a wide variety of topics: the culture of boxing gyms; the effects of highway construction in the Appalachian mountains; the experiences of HIV-positive women; Jews in mountainous villages of Azerbaijan; the lives of older schizophrenics institutionalized in the U.S.; the experiences of Mexican immigrants and their families in Chicago; and "colorism," prejudice within one's own racial community based on one's skin hue, documented and relived through graphic prints and oral interviews. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Historical Note
The year 2015 marked the 25th anniversary of the Dorothea Lange–Paul Taylor Prize, an award given by the Center for Documentary Studies. First announced a year after the Center's founding at Duke University, the prize was created to encourage collaboration between documentary writers and photographers in the tradition of the acclaimed photographer Dorothea Lange and writer and social scientist Paul Taylor. In 1941 Lange and Taylor published An American Exodus, a book that renders human experience eloquently in text and images and remains a seminal work in documentary studies. The Lange-Taylor Prize honors their important collaborative work.
The Lange-Taylor Prize is offered to a writer and a photographer in the early stages of a documentary project. By encouraging such collaborative efforts, the Center for Documentary Studies supports the documentary process in which writers and photographers work together to record the human story.
[Source: Center for Documentary Studies website, August 2010.]
Access Restrictions
Collections are open to research but are restricted to educational, non-commercial use.
Digital files have been migrated to a library server and are accessible only in the Rubenstein Library reading room on advance request.
Please contact the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library before coming to use this collection.
Provenance
The Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize Photography Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2007, 2011, and 2019.
Collection Overview
The Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor documentary prize is awarded by Duke University's Center for Documentary Studies to a writer and a photographer in the early stages of a documentary project. The collection comprises the work of seven documentary artists: Rob Amberg, Mary Berridge, Steven Cozart, Jason Eskenazi, Jim Lommasson, Dona Ann McAdams, and Daniel Ramos, totaling 91 color and black-and-white prints and four digital video files of interviews, all awarded the Lange-Taylor Prize.
The projects examine the culture of boxing gyms; the effects of highway construction in the Appalachian mountains; the experiences of HIV-positive women; Jews in the mountains of Azerbaijan; the lives of older schizophrenics; the experiences of Mexican immigrants and their families who have settled in Chicago; and "colorism," prejudice within one's own racial community based on one's skin hue, documented and relived through graphic prints and oral interviews. Several of the collections include paper copies of the artist's statements regarding their projects.
Some of these documentary artist's work was displayed as part of Hand and Eye: Fifteen Years of the Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize, an exhibit at the Center for Documentary Studies from September 19, 2005-January 8, 2006.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Related Material
Additional photographic work by Rob Amberg is found in the Rob Amberg Photographs collection and the Sodom Laurel Album Exhibition Photographs, both held in the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
African Americans -- Portraits; Boxing -- Photographs; Colorism -- Southern States; Documentary Photography -- Mexico; Documentary Photography -- United States; Jews -- Azerbaijan -- Photographs; HIV-positive women -- Portraits; Mexican Americans -- United States -- Ethnic identity; Mexicans -- Illinois -- Chicago -- Photographs; Mexicans -- Portraits; Racism -- North Carolina; Roads -- Design and construction -- Environmental aspects; Schizophrenia -- Social aspects; Schizophrenics -- Portraits; Working class -- Portraits; Azerbaijan -- Photographs; Chicago (Ill.) -- Photographs; Chicago (Ill.) -- Social conditions; Former Soviet republics -- Photographs; Madison County (N.C.) -- Photographs -- Photographs; Monterrey (Mexico) -- Photographs; Nuevo Leon (Mexico: State) -- Photographs; Black-and-white prints (photographs); Chromogenic color prints; Digital moving image formats; Gelatin silver prints; Inkjet prints; Oral histories (document genre); Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Mary Berridge: A Positive Life: Portraits of Women Living with HIV, 1996-2005; 22 items
  Scope and Contents note
  Twenty-two chromogenic color prints from the project A Positive Life: Portraits of Women Living with HIV, a collaboration between photographer Mary Berridge and writer River Houston to photograph and interview women in the North Carolina Triangle who are living with HIV/AIDS. The first five prints were published in the photobook by the same name. Winner of the 1996 Lange-Taylor Prize.
  Sixteen of the 22 prints are captioned on the back. Boxes 2, 3, and 5 house 20x24 prints, and Box 4 holds prints that are 34.5 x 28.5 inches.
  Biographical / Historical
  Mary Berridge is an author and documentary photographer based in Chapel Hill, North Carolina, where she is working on a book about autism and neurodiversity. She is deeply involved in community work to support and lobby for children with special needs. Berridge's photographs have been exhibited in many galleries and museums including the Museum of Modern Art in New York, The M.H. de Young Memorial Museum in San Francisco and the Museum of Fine Arts in Houston. Time magazine recently included her in a list of "unsung American female photographers of the past century".
  Prints from Berridge's AIDS project were exhibited in 1999 at the Duke University Center for Documentary Studies. For this work she was awarded the 1996 Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize by the Center for Documentary Studies.
  [Source: Photographer's website, October 2019]
  - Lery Espinosa, 27, diagnosed HIV-positive in 1994, infected through sex (Box 2)
  - Beatrice, 39, diagnosed HIV-positive in 1992, infected through sex (Box 2)
  - April Drew, 29, diagnosed HIV-positive in 1989, infected through sex (Box 2)
  - Laurie Priddy, 32, diagnosed HIV-positive in 1990, infected through sex (Box 2)
  - Brenda, 35, diagnosed HIV-positive in 1994, infected through sex (Box 2)
  - Unknown woman (Box 2)
  - Julie Evenson (Box 3)
  - Milsa "Cookie" Ramos (Box 3)
  - Meredith (Box 3)
  - Debbie Diamond (Box 3)
  - Tracie Edness-Etheredge (Box 3)
  - Alicia McWilliams (Box 3)
  - Shana Tenendah (Box 4)
  - Julie Evenson (Box 4)
  - Tracie Edness-Etheredge (Box 4)
  - Patricia Annichiarico (Box 4)
  - Woman sitting on couch smoking, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Women in green sitting outdoors in a chair, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Woman and young man standing beside a table, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Woman sitting on floor with dog and child, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Woman in white in front of magnolia [citrus?] tree, 1999, 2 copies (Box 5)
- Rob Amberg: I-26, Corridor of Change, 1996-2003; 4 items
  Four 16x20 gelatin silver prints from the documentary project I-26, Corridor of Change, by Rob Amberg and Sam Gray, an examination of the physical, economic, and social changes accompanying highway construction in the remote Appalachian mountains of North Carolina. A collection of Amberg's photographic images and publications are also held as a separate archive at the Rubenstein Library. Winner of the 1998 Lange-Taylor Prize.
  Rob Amberg (1947- ) moved to Madison County, North Carolina, in 1973 and began what has become his lifetime project – writing and photographing about the evolving culture and environment of his adopted county. He has published two photobooks about Madison County: Sodom Laurel Album (2002), and The New Road: I-26 and the Footprints of Progress in Appalachia (2009), and is currently working on a third book. His work is regularly published and exhibited nationally. The portfolio from the I-26 project was awarded the 1998 Lange-Taylor Prize by the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University.
  - Homemade sign mounted during exhumation of Little Iony Church Cemetery, Mars Hill, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Looking north from the visitor center overlook toward Dale and Lurethra Fluty's farm, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Power shovel churning land at Little Creek, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Supervisors inspect recent blast at Buckner's Gap, 1997 (Box 1)
- Jason Eskenazi: Mountain Jews: A Lost Tribe, 1999; 4 items
  Four 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints by photographer Jason Eskenazi that are part of the documentary project, Mountain Jews: A Lost Tribe, by Eskenazi and Jennifer Gould. These images of a customer getting a shave in a barber shop, men gathering at a crossroads to chat, women walking through a Jewish cemetery, and a village maternity ward are part of a project to document the transition of a centuries-old Jewish village in the Caucasus Mountains from its traditional ways of life. This work was awarded the 1999 Lange-Taylor Prize.
  Jason Eskenazi (1960- ) is an author, editor, and photographer based in New York City. He is best known for his trilogy of photobooks in which he documents Soviet Russia and New York's East and West Sides. Two of these books were published simultaneously in 2019. His work is held by the Brooklyn Museum and the Leica Gallery. Eskenazi co-founded Red Hook Editions, a publishing cooperative of photographers. He is co-creator of a photography zine/newspaper titled Dog Food, blending cynic philosophy and photography. He was awarded the 1999 Lange-Taylor Prize from the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University for his photographs of Jewish people in the village of Krasnayasloboda in Azerbaijan.
  [Source: Photographer's website and Wikipedia, October 2019]
  - A man gets a shave at the corner barber shop, Krasnaya Sloboda, 1999 (Box 1)
  - In the center of town, men gather at the crossroads everyday to chat, Krasnaya Sloboda, 1999 (Box 1)
  - The village maternity ward (a bird in the house is a bad omen), Krasnaya Sloboda, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Two women walk through an old Jewish cemetery on Tisha b'Av, Krasnaya Sloboda, 1999 (Box 1)
- Dona Ann McAdams: The Garden of Eden: Living with Schizophrenia on Coney Island, 1983-1998; 3 items
  Collection comprises three 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints published as part of the photobook The Garden of Eden: Living with Schizophrenia on Coney Island, by Dona Ann McAdams and Brad Kessler. The project documents through black-and-white photographic portraits the lives of institutionalized men and women with severe mental illness. This work was awarded the 2002 Lange-Taylor Prize.
  Dona Ann McAdams has been making photographs for over forty years. Her black-and-white images of performance artists, nuns, race track workers, people with schizophrenia, working farm animals, and anti-nuclear, pro-choice, war protest, feminist, queer liberation, and AIDS activism protests have has been exhibited at venues such as the Museum of Modern Art, The Whitney Museum of American Art, The International Center for Photography, and the Museum of Contemporary Art in Los Angeles, among other places.
  She is the recipient of the 2002 Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize awarded by the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University and numerous other awards and grants. She is currently based in Vermont.
  - Mary and the birds (Box 1)
  - Mary and the birds (Box 1)
  - Stillwell Avenue (Box 1)
- Jim Lommasson: Shadow Boxers: Sweat, Sacrifice, and the Will to Survive in America's Toughest Boxing Gyms, 1998-2003; 5 items
  Five black-and-white digital prints, approximately 19x15 inches, featuring portraits and close-ups of boxers, and a punching bag, taken in gyms in Philadelphia, Los Angeles, and Portland. The images were published as part of the photobook Shadow Boxers: Sweat, Sacrifice, and the Will to Survive in America's Toughest Boxing Gyms, by Jim Lommasson and Katherine Dunn, which speaks to the power of boxing to transform lives and communities. Lomasson's documentary project was awarded the 2004 Lange-Taylor Prize.
  Jim Lommasson is a freelance photographer and author living in Portland, Oregon. Lommasson received the 2004 Dorothea Lange–Paul Taylor Prize from The Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University for his first book, Shadow Boxers: Sweat, Sacrifice and The Will To Survive In American Boxing Gyms, Stone Creek Publications.
  - Azteca Boxing Gym, East Los Angeles, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Bryheim Douglas, The James Costello Boxing Gym, Philadelphia, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Hand Wraps, Virg "The Scourge" Bohnenkamp, The Grand Avenue Boxing Gym, Portland, Oregon, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Saul Hernandez, The Grand Avenue Boxing Gym, Portland, Oregon, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Wild Card Boxing Gym, Los Angeles, 2003 (Box 1)
- Steven M. Cozart: The Pass/Fail Series, 2013-2019; 1.0 Linear Feet 5 prints; 36 Gigabytes 4 digital video files (2 .mov, 1 .mp4, 1 .wmv)
  Scope and Contents
  Series comprises four digital video files and five photographic prints from Cozart's body of work, The Pass/Fail Series. The color prints range in size from 8x12 inches to 13x25 inches and incorporate a portrait of the interviewee and a text excerpt from the oral interview. The four video files contain excerpts from interviews with individuals concerning their experiences with discrimination and racism within their own communities. The "Brown Paper Bag Test" is used as both a point of reference to begin the conversation and is also used as the surface to create the images. Cozart's work was awarded the 2016 Lange-Taylor Prize.
  From the artist's statement: "Working as both a visual artist and documentarian, I interview family members, friends, and acquaintances about their experiences of race, skin tone, hair texture, and masculinity in relation to other African Americans." A full statement is included in the prints folder.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Images printed on Moab Lasal Photo Matte archival acid-free paper, smooth surface, heavy weight (230 gsm/154 lb.). Printed with Canon Lucia Inks on an inkjet printer by the Fine Works Color Lab (Hahnemuhle Certified).
  Biographical Note
  A native of Durham, North Carolina, Steven M. Cozart now lives and works in Greensboro, North Carolina. Cozart received his Bachelor of Pine Arts degree in Art Education with a concentration in Printmaking and Drawing from East Carolina University. In addition to being a freelance artist and illustrator, he is also a teacher in the Guilford County School System, where he has taught since 1995. Currently, he teaches Visual Art and Computer Graphics at Weaver Academy for Performing and Visual Art and Advanced Technologies. He was awarded the 2016 Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize from the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University.
  - Photographic prints
    - The difference between ants: Parts I-IV, 13x25 inches (Box 6)
    - The Harrington interview, 12x18 inches (Box 6)
    - The Baines interview 1, 10x18 inches (Box 6)
    - True value? (Right here), 9x17 inches (Box 6)
    - The Watkins interview, 8x12 inches (Box 6)
  - Digital video files
    Conditions Governing Access
    Digital files are open for research and may only be accessed in the Rubenstein Library by advance request. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
    - Edith Cozart I_Unedited, 2013 June 29; 1241 Megabytes 1 digital video file (.mov) Total Running Time: 00:07:46 (Digital-materials RL00795-SET-0001)
      Unedited footage of interview with Edith Cozart about Colorism.
    - Edith Cozart III_Unedited, 2013 June 29; 1.08 Gigabytes 1 digital video file (.mov) Total Running Time: 00:06:47 (Digital-materials RL00795-SET-0001)
    - Johncarlos Miller Interview_Unedited, 2017 November 3; 1.02 Gigabytes 1 digital video file (.wmv) Total Running Time: 00:13:51 (Digital-materials RL00795-SET-0001)
      Unedited footage of interview with Johncarlos Miller about Colorism.
    - Pass_Fail_Interviews_EDITED, 2019 July 16; 2.1 Gigabytes 1 digital video file (.mp4) Total Running Time: 00:09:36 (Digital-materials RL00795-SET-0001)
      Edited documentary of several subjects, including the artist about Colorism.
- Daniel Ramos: The Land of Illustrious Men, 1999-2019; 48 items 2 boxes
  Collection of 48 black-and-white and color inkjet prints of images and photo collages by Daniel Ramos, winner of the 2018 Lange-Taylor Prize.. The project, The Land of Illustrious Men, examines the lives of people who have left their home country to pursue a different and improved life for themselves and for their families in the U.S. Taken in Monterrey, Mexico and in Chicago, Illinois, the photographs include portraits of Ramos's family members and friends in households or in outdoor settings, often surrounded with familiar and meaningful objects. There are also images of graffiti, burial sites, and other locations. A few of the collages include typed narrative text describing the family's migration from Mexico, and life as an immigrant family in Chicago. A photobook by the same name has been cataloged separately and can be located in the Duke Libraries catalog.
  From the artist's statement: " 'The Land Of Illustrious Men' is a photo-novella of my life as a son of working-class immigrants who came to America from Mexico in search of a better life. The series offers the viewer a glimpse of the personal story of each member of my family, and reveals the nature of their relationship to one another. I include my own experience - a childhood spent living between two worlds, and my decision to reject the blue-collar tradition that was to be my presumed legacy in order to become a photographer... Although my journey is personal, this project is an expression of a larger story about immigration, cultural identity, assimilation, and class that is shared and felt by many."
  Daniel Ramos (1978- ) is a documentary artist based in Chicago and Monterrey, Mexico. He graduated from Columbia College Chicago with a BA in Photography in 2003, and studied for an MFA at California College of the Arts in 2007. His work has been featured in CPW's "Photography Now" 2018 exhibition, AI-AP Latin American Fotografia 7, and the Lenscratch DeveloperXFor Freedoms online gallery. Daniel had his first solo show for his series, "The Land of Illustrious Men," at Filter Space in Chicago, Illinois in July, 2019. This work was awarded the 2018 Dorothea Lange-Paul Taylor Prize awarded by the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University, and was featured in the New York Times "Lens" feature, and PDN Edu. A full artist's atatement is available in the collection.
  Prints were created with an Epson Inket Jet Printer 9000 on Canson Plantine Fiber Rag, and printed with archival Epson inks. They range in size from 8 1/2 x 10 1/2 inches to 17 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches.
  - An education, 2018; 16 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 7)
    Photo collage; Chicago, Illinois
  - Angels, 2014; 13 x 10 1/5 inches (Box 8)
  - Coyote, 2018; 17 1/4 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 7)
  - For teen, A.K.A. Victor, 2018; 15 1/2 x 10 1/2 inches (Box 7)
  - Grandma's home, 2000; 16 1/2 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
    Lampazos De Naranjo, Nuevo Leon, Mexico
  - Arriving at the Monterrey bus terminal, 2000; 16 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
    Monterrey, Nuevo Leon, Mexico
  - View of Monterey from La Colonia Independencia, 2002; 16 3/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 7)
  - Winter rooftops, 1999; 17 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 7)
    Chicago, Illinois
  - My grandmother visits the graves of her daughter and her mother, 2014; 17 x 11 inches (Box 7)
  - My parents waiting at the train station, 2000; 16 x 11 inches (Box 7)
  - My mother, my father, and uncle Ramiro on the way to Monterrey, 2000; 17 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
  - My mother outside the liquor store, 1999; 16 3/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
  - The Harlem stop on the Blue Line, 2001; 16 1/2 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
    Berwyn, Illinois
  - El Conejo bus stop, Laredo, 2000; 16 3/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
    Laredo, Texas
  - Our apartment in Pilsen, 1999; 17 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 7)
  - Abuela, 2002; 13 1/2 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 8)
  - Pilo in leaves, 2016; 14 1/4 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 7)
  - Tomb, 2003; 13 3/4 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 8)
  - Self portrait at Sloan, 2002; 13 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 7)
    Franklin Park, Illinois
  - My grandfather Pedro, 2001; 13 1/4 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 8)
    Iramuco, Guanajuato, Mexico
  - Pharaoh of Highway 1, 2018; 13 1/2 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 8)
  - Kids in the junkyard, 2016; 13 x 10 1/4 inches (Box 8)
  - Grandpa Pedro's kitchen, 2001; 14 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
  - Graffiti 2, 2016; 11 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
  - Graffiti 1, 2016; 11 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
  - Heart, 2000; 12 x 12 inches (Box 7)
    Guanajuato, Guanajuato, Mexico
  - All of my help comes from the Lord, 2015; 12 x 12 inches (Box 7)
  - The graveyard where my mother is buried, 2016; 11 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
  - Tio Ramiro, 2000; 11 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
  - Rio Santa Catarina, 2015; 11 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
  - My mother's burial site, 2016; 11 3/4 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 7)
  - Two flowers, 2015; 11 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
    Highland Park, Illinois
  - Frida And Diego, 2014; 10 1/2 x 10 1/2 inches (Box 8)
    Coyoacan, Mexico City, Mexico
  - Jonathan, 2017; 11 1/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 7)
  - Maximiliano at the Indiana Dunes State Park, 2015; 11 3/4 x 11 3/4 inches (Box 7)
    Indiana
  - Self portrait, 2002; 11 1/4 x 11 inches (Box 8)
  - Kristina And Maximiliano, 2016; 11 1/2 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 7)
  - Water park, 2016; 10 3/4 x 10 3/4 inches (Box 8)
  - David, 2017; 9 3/4 x 12 inches (Box 8)
  - Lupita, 2017; 9 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 8)
  - My father after work, 2002; 9 1/4 x 11 1/2 inches (Box 8)
  - Our bathroom, 1999; 7 3/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 8)
  - Flushing lamp, 2017; 9 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 8)
  - The land of illustrious men, 2018; 9 3/4 x 11 1/4 inches (Box 8)
  - Grandma at the table, 2017; 8 1/2 x 10 1/2 inches (Box 8)
  - Mela as a young woman, 2019; 9 x 11 inches (Box 8)
    Archival inkjet print. Image of a vintage photograph, 1940s?
  - Mother, father, myself and the family yard, 2018; 11 1/2 x 9 1/2 inches (Box 8)
    Photo collage; Chicago, Illinois, inkjet print with acrylic marker
  - Vandalism, 2018; 15 x 12 inches (Box 7)
    Chicago, Illinois, inkjet print with acrylic marker. Note: this print appears last in the artist's inventory, but due to size, has been housed with the first group of prints.